"Health Insurance-related GoM work
also requires more time..
so they have gone to take more time..
as to why it had to have more time?
and therefore the insurance regulators
input is awaited."
"IRDAI, the Insurance Regulatory
and Development Authority's inputs have not arrived.
So, the GoM felt that it needed a bit more time."
After charging 18% GST on life and health insurance for years,
the government has now finally realised..
Similar to world class developed economies,
If we can't provide better quality
free public healthcare to our citizens.
And If a common man, from his own savings..
If he is considering to
purchase a security for his own family..
which ideally is his fundamental right.
Hence, GST should not be levied on such basic necessities.
While the news is great.
But, I can't just praise someone for doing the bare minimum.
I want to praise someone for going
the extra mile for the benefit of the citizens.
Although, speaking of benefit..
Will this 18% GST removal benefit
will be passed onto you?
Or is there a catch here?
We will explore it in this video.
My name is Money Minded Mandeep.
Welcome back to the channel!
[INTRO MUSIC]
Is Insurance Tax-Free now?
First things first, what's the news?
18% GST, which was levied on
all the life and health insurance policies.
The GST won't be imposed
on the premium from now onwards.
This means all kinds of life insurance policies,
i.e. Term Insurance..
and Traditional policies,
i.e. Money Back or Guaranteed Income.
along with ULIPs (Unit Linked Insurance Plan).
And health insurance policies,
both individual and floater plan.
And the news is..
If you pay the premiums of any of these policies
after 22nd September, 2025.
then GST won't be levied on those premium.
Whether it's a new policy or an old one.
But the catch is..
If you pay the premium for future coverage in advance today.
For example, If you pay the health insurance premium
for up to three years today itself.
The 18% GST you've paid on that.
You won't receive a refund on it.
The premium you would pay in the fourth year,
it will be GST free.
The bottom line is the premiums you have paid until now.
You won't receive GST on that.
But, GST won't be levied henceforth (from the fourth year).
Benefits for Existing Policyholders
What benefits will the existing customers receive?
The premium generated on your life or health insurance,
after 22nd September.
It will be roughly 15% lesser.
Although 18% GST has been reduced.
Let's presume you were paying ₹15,000
on an average towards Term Insurance.
and it was inclusive of 18% GST.
It means the cost of the insurance premium was ₹12,750.
The remaining was GST.
It means you are saving ₹2,250 on a premium of ₹15,000.
That is a discount of 15%.
And If your annual health insurance premium costs ₹30,000.
So from now on it will cost ₹25,500.
i.e. savings of ₹4,500.
And this is just one individual's policy.
I pay more than ₹1 lakh in premiums,
both for health and life.
It means I will be able to save ₹15,000.
You can calculate the savings yourself.
Benefit for New Policyholders
Now let's talk about new customers.
You must take advantage of the opportunity.
You will receive up to a 20% discount
on Term Insurance premiums.
We are not talking about the GST benefit.
You will receive that anyway.
I have mentioned Policy Bazaar's link
in the video's description and top comment.
Click on it once.
Go to 'Term Insurance'.
Enter your 'Age' and 'Existing diseases'.
You will see, based on the average cost of ₹1,800..
a person similar to my age is receiving
a ₹3 crore term insurance cover.
A few months ago, when I was researching..
Cover worth ₹2 crores was available for ₹1,800.
Today, it's available for ₹3 crores.
But, this is a very small window.
Because such discounts are never available.
If you want your policy to start after 22nd September,
for you to pay 0% on GST.
Even that is possible.
Needless to say, this is not a paid video..
wherein I am getting money for complimenting about the product.
I have come here to provide you an information.
So that you could avail a few extra discounts.
If you would like to support us indirectly,
without spending extra money..
I will only request you one thing..
The Policy Bazaar link has been provided
in the description and the top comment.
Please click on that link and purchase the insurance,
because you will receive heavy discounts through that link.
You won't have to spend an extra penny.
And we will be motivated to create
more such educational videos for you in the future..
and to educate you free of cost.
You will receive 'Full Claim Support'
and 'Relationship' on Policy Bazaar.
In fact, If you have old age parents
and you aren't staying with them.
The policy bazaar team even visits your house
and will admit your parents at the hospital.
The team handles the documentation and claim support.
And If you have to call the team multiple times for any reason..
So the person on the other end of the call
would be your Relationship Manager,
who knows your medical background,
policy details, etc, beforehand.
You won't have to dial multiple numbers
and speak to different people.
and neither will you have to explain the entire story again.
Currently, great prices, great service!
Hence, I keep encouraging you.
And I have purchased my own policy from Policy Bazaar.
Talking about Health Insurance.
The premiums are cheaper by 10% to 15% here.
And as I mentioned before..
Even after purchasing health insurance,
it's premiums keep increasing with your age.
Unlike term insurance, whose premium is fixed.
Right now, if you look at the premiums
for some of the good plans out there.
Good plans indicate good company track record,
resolved complaint data..
All the features included in the plan are as per your preference.
And the hidden conditions are minimum.
I have explained about such plans in detail
in my 'Ultimate Guide to Health Insurance' video.
Although, this is a 50-minute-long video,
but it's worth every minute.
Because, with a lot of patience..
I have read the fine print of the company..
and explained how to
interpret the hidden terms and conditions.
But If I were to explain in short,
then I have compared HDFC's Optima Secure plan
and ICICI's Elevate plan.
If I check the premiums of such plans,
then Optima Secure, in which you will receive
₹10 lakhs + ₹10 lakhs cover..
it's premium is approximately ₹14,000/ annually, for my age.
And in ICICI Elevate, you will receive ₹10 lakh cover
for approximately ₹8,500/ annually.
Although this is incomplete,
because there is a cap on room rent.
For which you will have to opt for an additional rider
to remove the room rent cap.
And after adding a few necessary riders,
the premium could increase.
And I explained such technicalities
in the 50-minute-long video.
But overall, these premiums are great.
Because, in such plans, your total coverage in the next three to five years,
will either triple or quadruple..
depending on their individual bonuses and restoration policies.
Premiums will increase in future
Now, why do I think this is the best time for you
to purchase life and term insurance both?
1. The first one is quite logical,
that 'Disasters do not occur with prior warning.'
What If something happens tomorrow?
What were you waiting for?
Stating that you will purchase the policy later.
No, you must purchase it today.
It's as simple as that.
The second answer is that insurance is related to business.
For that you need to understand, 'Input Tax Credit'.
Now, GST is a 'Sales Tax'.
Whenever the company does a sale,
they charge GST from the customer..
and then proceed to pay the GST to the government.
But the company doesn't just sell.
It also purchases, i.e. they also incur expenses.
The company has to pay GST on those expenses too.
What are the type of expenses in an insurance business?
Agent commission, office rent, professional services,
office equipment such as laptop, TV, AC, sofa, etc.
So let's understand this with an example.
Presume that the insurance company
did a sale of ₹5,000 crore.
It means they received a premium costing ₹5,000 crores.
But there is an 18% GST levied on it too.
Hence, the gross sales have been drawn as ₹5,900 crores.
And in the past one year, the insurance company
has incurred ₹1,000 crore in expenses.
On that, 18% GST, i.e. they have paid ₹180 crore GST.
Now this sales GST, i.e. ₹900 crore..
which they have charged customers along with the insurance premium.
The company's responsibility is to deposit
this ₹900 crore to the government.
But the government offers a benefit
which is known as 'Input Tax Credit'.
What it means is,
The GST collected by you at the time of sales
amounting to ₹900 crores.
While deposting the same.
You can deduct the already paid
GST of ₹180 crore at the time of expenses.
Now this company will pay
₹720 crores as Net GST to the government.
And they will receive the Input Tax Credit of ₹180 crores.
So their profit would be..
Gross Revenue, i.e. ₹5,900 crores - Cost i.e. ₹1,180 crores - ₹720 crore,
which is paid to the government.
What's left is ₹4,000 crores.
Now, If it's not allowed to charge GST
on sales of upto ₹5,000 crores.
which means If you are not receiving those ₹900 crores.
The company doesn't owe the government anything.
There is no need to deposit any GST.
And If there is no need to deposit GST,
then ₹180 crores paid in the form of expenses.
How will you claim that?
In such a case, the company's equation will change.
On the ₹5,000 crore revenue,
they will have to subtract the cost of ₹1,180 crore..
and their profit would be ₹3,820 crore.
It means, if you don't receive input tax credit,
then the company's cost will increase by 18%.
Now, tell me this..
Are companies charitable organisations?
Will they keep providing you with services
at a higher cost of 18%..
Will they keep selling insurance
and won't increase the premiums?
If you were a shareholder of such a company,
would you have been happy with this decision?
"Our investment is worth ₹35 lakhs,
then how did we incur a loss of ₹36 lakhs?"
Now I am not trying to scare you.
I am not saying that the premiums will increase by 18%.
In fact, the opposite is happening.
A minimum deduction of 10% to 15%
has been imposed from today onwards.
It's happening based on the assumption
that insurance adoption would increase.
More people will be able to afford insurance policies.
The higher cost will be offset by higher sales volume.
And the biggest advantage of GST deduction
will reflect in term and health insurance policies.
Because these are pure risk policies.
The companies don't have to pay anything
until there is a claim request.
Whereas, the other life insurance policies,
which has 'investment components'..
such as Money Back, Guaranteed Income or ULIP plans.
There is a maturity value in this..
It's a huge amount,
which the company has to pay.
In such plans, to pass on the entire benefit
of GST deduction to customers,
doesn't seem like a sensible option.
But why should we care?
We have always told that term and health insurance
are the most important insurances.
And you will be receiving a benefit on that.
But this benefit will keep reducing gradually.
Due to the absence of input tax credit.
So my suggestion for you is to purchase term insurance..
and lock the cheapest premium today.
Because they will be same for your lifetime.
Any benefit of health insurance
that you are able to view today.
It could also reduce a bit in the future.
Because companies will eventually transfer
the higher costs on to you.
But not today!
Hence, take an action today itself.
And you already know that,
I have been empowering you to take
well informed action for the past several years.
Hence, I am providing you two links in the description..
Term Insurance Guide and Health Insurance Guide of 2025.
The weekend is approaching.
Take out some time and watch it.
Also I have one request..
If you want to support us wholeheartedly,
and not without money..
i.e. not by paying extra money.
The Policy Bazaar link which you will find
in top comment and description.
Click on it and purchase the policy
directly from the link.
Because, you will receive great discounts on them.
You will be able to support us indirectly through it.
So that we keep educating you in the future, free of cost.
I will meet you in another new video!
Until then, All the best!
Happy Insurance Shopping!